Boker tov בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's daf דף daf is tes
ט, tes, but we are behind, so we start on the bottom
of chet amud aleph ח עמוד א. chet amud aleph. You ready?
I'm ready, but it's not...
I keep
pushing you up.
Okay, fine.
So today's daf דף daf is is tes ט, tes, but we
start on the bottom of chet amud aleph ח עמוד א chet
amud aleph in the Gemara גמרא Gemara after the Mishnah משנה. Mishnah.
The Mishnah משנה Mishnah is now focusing on or moving from the
chatas חטאת chatas which are served for kaparah כפרה kaparah for for
kares כרת kares or for sins of kares כרת kares to a
chatas חטאת chatas which is about which is about part of a
tahara טהרה tahara process, which will be more explicit in the next
perek פרק, perek,
and so we have so we're now on the Mishnah משנה Mishnah
that speak that we're dealing with the issue about a chatas חטאת
chatas that's brought after the end of a leida לידה leida process,
and the Mishnah משנה Mishnah that spoke about what happens in the
case where a woman is a safek ספק safek having given birth
multiple times or a safek ספק safek having been a zavah זבה
zavah multiple times, so she needs to bring this chatas חטאת chatas
in order to allow her to eat kodshim קדשים. kodshim. This is
called mechusrei kaparah מחוסרי כפרה, mechusrei kaparah, it's going to be the
explicit topic of the next perek פרק, perek, which is coming up.
But here it deals specifically with the issue that there are times
where she could bring one for many, that was the previous Mishnah
משנה, Mishnah, based on when she if she had multiple births or
miscarriages within certain times. And here we're dealing with the fact that
if she doesn't know if she has to bring it, maybe it
was a miscarriage that was after 40 days, maybe it was before
40 days, what does she do? Because she still needs to bring
at least one in order to eat the kodshim קדשים. kodshim. So
the basic point was fine, you bring one and the rest because
they are safek ספק, safek, you don't eat it. But then it
ended with the fascinating story which some people love to quote of
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel,
who spoke about a case where if there were five definite chatos
חטאות chatos for a leida לידה leida or zivah זיבה, zivah, so
one would be enough to eat kodshim קדשים, kodshim, but the rest
would still remain an obligation. So you only need to bring one,
you know, if you're tamei טמא tamei to allow any one sort
of is the tahara טהרה tahara process and allows you to eat
kodshim קדשים, kodshim, but the rest still are your obligation if you're
vadai ודאי vadai obligated, definitely obligated. And the Gemara גמרא Gemara speaks
about how there was a high demand and low supply and there
was a very high price. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel basically, you know, said that women wouldn't
have to bring and and that drove down the demand and it
also significantly drove down the price. So on the one hand, you
know, that was an act of she would rabbinic legalistic activism. It
did not make a woman tahor טהור tahor that was tamei טמא,
tamei, she still brought one, but it basically told her that she
didn't have to do her full obligation of korbanos קרבנות korbanos as
a way of addressing, you know, a significant problem. And I should
mention, I'm mentioning this because the Gemara גמרא Gemara doesn't discuss it,
that there are other cases where specific activism around the question of
prices was done. For example, there was a time where in certain
communities they would basically say it's assur אסור assur to buy fish
for Shabbos שבת Shabbos until the price of fish goes down. Or,
you know, we're not allowed other types of things, which is, you
know, which was like not it was more like a passive resistance,
passive we're not doing certain obligations, it wasn't an active violation, and
but you do have examples where those types of things were done,
costs of lulav לולב lulav and esrog אתרוג, esrog,
those types of things to drive down the cost. Yes, so much
to learn there.
Right, exactly. Okay, so now let's take a look at the Gemara
גמרא. Gemara. The Gemara גמרא Gemara is not going to focus on
the last line, it focuses on the first half. Tanu Rabbanan תנו
רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: Hei leidos vadai ve-hei zivos safek ה לידות ודאי
וה זיבות ספק... Hei leidos vadai ve-hei zivos safek... I'm sorry, I
just went blank. Hei leidos vadai ve-hei zivos safek ה לידות ודאי
וה זיבות ספק, Hei leidos vadai ve-hei zivos safek, o hei leidos
vadai ve-hei leidos safek או ה לידות ודאי וה לידות ספק, o
hei leidos vadai ve-hei leidos safek, mevia shetei kinim מביאה שתי קינים.
mevia shetei kinim. So there's actually a question here in the girsa
גרסא, girsa, what a surprise. Anyway, so the better girsa גרסא girsa
is that it's in pairs. Hei zivos vadai ve-hei zivos safek ה
זיבות ודאי וה זיבות ספק, Hei zivos vadai ve-hei zivos safek, o
hei leidos vadai ve-hei leidos safek או ה לידות ודאי וה לידות
ספק. o hei leidos vadai ve-hei leidos safek. Okay, so so basically
a woman has a case where she has like five births which
she definitely was obligated in, you know, and five which each which
was a safek ספק, safek, or the same with a zivah זיבה.
zivah. So how does she deal with that? So it's sort of
like the case of the Mishnah משנה Mishnah except it's both scenarios
at once, both the vadai ודאי vadai collection of of experiences and
the safek ספק. safek. So what is the halacha הלכה? halacha? Mevia
shetei kinim מביאה שתי קינים. Mevia shetei kinim. She brings two birds.
Achas al ha-vadai ve-achas al ha-safek אחת על הודאי ואחת על הספק.
Achas al ha-vadai ve-achas al ha-safek. One for the ones you're definitely
obligated for, one for the ones you're doubtfully obligated. Shel vadai ne-echeles
ve-hashar alei hova של
ודאי נאכלת והשאר עליה חובה. Shel vadai ne-echeles ve-hashar alei hova. The
one that you're definitely obligated, if you have five that you're obligated,
as we said, only one is needed at the end, you know,
any one is the tahara טהרה tahara process and now the woman
can eat kodshim קדשים, kodshim, but the rest are definite obligation and
eventually have to be brought. Shel safek של ספק, Shel safek, if
there were five doubtful, ein ne-echeles ve-ein hashar alei hova אין נאכלת
ואין השאר עליה חובה. ein ne-echeles ve-ein hashar alei hova. You just
basically forget about that and you don't eat them, I mean you
don't forget, meaning you bring one because for the tahara טהרה tahara
process, but you don't eat it because when you bring a chatas
חטאת, chatas, a bird chatas חטאת chatas for a tahara טהרה tahara
process it's not eaten, and you don't bring the rest because they
are doubtfully obligated to begin with, you only brought one for the
tahara טהרה tahara process. Now what's a little bit not clear here
is, is since you're bringing one, if they both happened at the
same time, then why not just bring one of the vadai ודאי
vadai and that would also cover the safek ספק, safek, right? Worst
case scenario you have ten obligations. Fine, so you bring one and
you're יוצא yotze the טהרה taharah process. Why do you have to
bring another one for the ודאי vadai and one for the ספק?
safek? So it is quite possible that this really does not mean
that they happened at the same time. It's really talking about different
scenarios, meaning it's not two scenarios, one scenario five and five, the
other five and five, it's four scenarios. Meaning if you have scenarios
of ודאי, vadai, you bring one ודאי vadai and the rest you
and you eat it and the rest you have to bring. And
if you have a scenario of ספק, safek, you bring one, you
don't eat it, and the rest you don't. Okay, but not that
they happen together. If the ודאי vadai and the ספק safek happen
together, then presumably you could bring one and for the ודאי vadai
and it certainly covers you for the ספק safek as well. Okay,
so that's the first stage. רבי יוחנן בן נורי אומר, Rabbi Yochanan
ben Nuri omer, הודאי תאמר על האחרונה ותיפטר. havadai tomar al ha'achrona
vetipater. שהספק, shehasafek, אם יש ודאי... im yesh vadai...
I'm sorry, how do you read this? One second, I gotta check
the גירסא girsa here.
One minute. Right. Okay. הודאי תאמר על
האחרונה ותיפטר.
havadai tomar al ha'achrona
vetipater.
Let's say she has five obligations. So we're assuming four different scenarios.
Either two of זיבה, ziva, two of יולדת. yoledet. Anyway, the point
is there are scenarios of ספק, safek, there are scenarios of ודאי.
vadai. So now comes along רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben
Nuri and he says like this: if she has five of ודאי,
vadai, so she has to say תאמר על האחרונה ותיפטר. tomar al
ha'achrona vetipater. She has to say that she brings one קרבן korban
and that's finishing up her, that's the end of her טהרה taharah
process, that's dealing with her טומאה, tumah, right? The rest are just
an obligation. Then when she brings the one קרבן, korban, she says,
"This is for my last birth. This is for my last זב."
zav. And since it's for the last and it's מטהר metaher the
last, and also it's מטהר metaher everything that preceded, it purifies. And
then the rest are just an obligation. But if she would say,
"This is for my first childbirth or my first זב," zav, so
then it's מטהר metaher the earlier thing, but the later טומאות tumot
came later and it doesn't work. You understand? Sequentially she had one
on January, one February, one March, one April, one May. She brings
it in June. When she brings one in June, that's enough for
the טהרה taharah process even though the rest are an obligation. Does
she say, if she says this one in June is for the
May, so if it's מטהר metaher the May, it's מטהר metaher everything
that preceded. But if she says this one in June is for
the January birth, okay, it's מטהר metaher the January birth, but then
you became טמא tamei after in March, April, May. So therefore he
says, even though you brought it at the end, if you designate
it for an earlier one, it's not מטהר metaher the birth that
came after.
This is really a poor choice of words to say ותיפטר vetipater
because you're not...
not ותיפטר, vetipater, it means that it works for the...
it works more like ותיטהר. vetitaher.
Right, that is the point because we're still saying that the rest
remain an obligation. של ספק, shel safek, now if she's bringing for
the, they were five in five months but they were all doubtful,
then אם יש ודאי ביניהם תאמר על הודאי ותיפטר. im yesh vadai
beineihem tomar al havadai vetipater.
So if there is one amongst the ספק safek that's a ודאי,
vadai, you had four births, one you were definite, one was a
ודאי vadai and four were ספק, safek, it was all a mix.
So fine, you bring the קרבן korban for the ודאי vadai and
you're exempt. ואם לאו, ve'im lav, if they were all ספק, safek,
which is the classic scenario we're dealing with, תאמר על אחד מהם
ותיפטר. tomar al echad meihem vetipater. Then if it's five ספק, safek,
she doesn't have to say, "This was for the March one," or
the whatever, the May one. If there were five ספק, safek, she
could say, "This is for any one of them," and then it
works for the טהרה taharah process. Now that's a little bizarre because
again, if she, if you have to designate the last one and
these are all doubtful, so maybe the ones that followed were a
טומאה tumah proper. But anyway, we'll see about that in the גמרא.
gemara. But that's what he says. His basic point is at least
for the ודאי vadai case, for the טהרה taharah to work, you
have to designate it for the very last. If it's earlier, then
the טומאה tumah comes back. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says, בין על הודאי בין על הספק תאמר על
אחד מהם ותיפטר. bein al havadai bein al hasafek tomar al echad
meihem vetipater. I don't care whether it's ודאי vadai or ספק, safek,
anytime you bring one קרבן, korban, that purifies you whether you're saying
it's for an earlier thing or later thing. You brought the קרבן
korban now, it's מטהר metaher you now, whatever you say that it's
for, you know, whatever you say it's for the sake of. Okay,
so that's the issue. So the first part was just again, presumably
they didn't mean all at the same time, the ודאי vadai and
the ספק. safek. It was just saying by a ודאי vadai you
bring one, you're טהור, tahor, you have an obligation. By a ספק
safek you bring one, you don't have an obligation, and you don't
even eat the one you brought. And now the real focus is
the question about when you bring that one that is מטהר metaher
you even though you still have an obligation, so does it have
to be designated for the last of them or can it even
be for a previous event? So let's take a look. אמר ליה
רב נחמן בר יצחק לרב פפא, Amar lei Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak
leRav Pappa, רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak said to
רב פפא, Rav Pappa, אימא לך משמיה דרבא, eima lach mishmei deRava,
I'll tell you something in the name of רבא. Rava. הני תנאי
במאי פליגי, hanei tannai bemai peligi, what is this debate about whether
you have to designate it for the last one or not? דרבי
יוחנן בן נורי מדמי להו לחטאת. deRabbi Yochanan ben Nuri medamei lehu
lechatat. רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri
that says you have to designate it for the last one says
that this is like a חטאת. chatat. Now it actually is a
חטאת, chatat, but what he means is it's like purifying for sin.
Purifying for טומאה tumah is like purifying for sin. So let's say
a person did five sins. Okay, what would we say? דמאן דחייב
חמש חטאות, deman dechayav chamesh chataot, somebody who did... עד דמייתי
כולהו ad d'mayisei kuleihu בסוף מכפר ליה besof mechaper lei
you're not atoned for until you bring all of the sin offerings.
So if you brought one you still have the other sins. Okay,
so therefore here it has to be at the end. Now it's
not a great analogy because by a חטאת chatas if you want
to be cleansed of all your sins you need all five חטאות.
chataos. Here to be cleansed of your טומאה tumah you only need
one קרבן. korban. So but the point is at least the analogy
enough is is that it has to basically somehow come at the
end to clean everything up. Okay, again it's not a great analogy.
הכא נמי לא שנא. hacha nami lo shnai.
Here too as well in order for it to cleanse it has
to cleanse for at least it has to be at least for
the last. רבי עקיבא מדמי לה לטבילה. Rabbi Akiva midami lah l'tevilah.
Rabbi Akiva says no
it's like going to the מקוה. mikvah. דמאן דחייב טבילות d'man d'chayeiv
tevilos
somebody that became טמא tamei five different ways and is obligated to
go to the מקוה. mikvah. You don't have to go to the
מקוה mikvah five times. So once he touched the שרץ, sheretz, once
he touched the corpse, or whatever, five שרצים, shratzim, whatever he did,
he goes to the מקוה mikvah once and he's done. He can
make a big announcement, I'm only going to the מקוה mikvah for
the first time I touched the שרץ. sheretz. It doesn't matter. Once
you go to the מקוה mikvah that cleanses you. Here too once
you bring the קרבן korban it cleanses you. כיון דטבל חדא
זימנא איטר. keivan d'taval chada zimna itar. Once you go to the
מקוה mikvah once, whatever however you designate the purpose, it is a
cleansing act for all the טומאות. tumos. הכא נמי לא שנא. hacha
nami lo shnai.
Here too it doesn't matter. So that's a nice little comparison and
actually Dov sent me an email he wanted like me to say
something about why is it that you have a חטאת chatas here
that's not exactly sin related. Talked about a חטאת היולדת chatas hayoledes
and it ties back to points we've discussed in the past which
is also like we discussed the idea of a חטאת chatas when
there wasn't any personal fault like the case of תינוק שנשבה. tinok
shenishba. That really the Torah's idea of a חטאת chatas as opposed
to an אשם asham is much more about the cleansing of the
metaphysical sin. It is not about the personal guilt and somehow the
cleansing of the person as much as it is about the cleansing
of the sin. And the words חיטוי chitoi and חטא cheit in
the Torah have much more to do with purifying and cleansing than
it does you know sort of than it sort of about atoning.
So therefore here too that's why חטאת chatas can function and that's
the next פרק perek as a way of part of a טהרה
taharah process and therefore the key concept by חטאת chatas is not
כפרה. kaparah. It's טהרה. taharah. The cleansing of the sin or here
the cleansing of the טומאה tumah state. No but once you say
it's...
no but once you...
no no no because it's about cleansing. So you could cleanse sin
and you could cleanse a טומאה tumah state. It doesn't have to
be about it's not about guilt and and liability and atonement it's
about cleansing. Right.
So you could say it's almost like you're cleansing God.
No no no you're cleansing a certain well there's like a metaphysical
reality that has been ruptured like the case he gave before about
the תינוק שנשבה. tinok shenishba. Somebody that grew up thinking they were
not Jewish and they violated שבת. Shabbos. There's absolutely no fault or
guilt that the person has. Right. But שבת Shabbos has been violated.
That's some metaphysical rupture that's some sin out there that needs to
be cleansed. Look the Torah talks about it that way. It says
like הארץ לא יכופר ha'aretz lo yechupar וטמאה הארץ. v'timah ha'aretz. There's
some effect of sin out there that needs to be cleansed.
Like with the child what is the sin?
So by child no so I'm saying it's not about sin. The
גמרא Gemara actually there is one גמרא Gemara that tries to say
you know the sin is that the woman swears she's not going
to whatever but the more I would say dominant and פשט pshat
approach here is that it's not about sin that it's about about
cleansing. Cleansing from what? טומאה. tumah. Now you can ask why does
childbirth have טומאה? tumah? That's a separate discussion. Okay but it's about
the same way it's part of a זב zav and a זבה
zavah also bring it. It's not about sin by a זב zav
and זבה. zavah. It's about the the cleansing. The Torah uses the
word חטאת chatas right?
חיטוי. chitoi. You could look at it you know speak about the
פרה אדומה. parah adumah. הוא יתחטא בו ביום השלישי וביום השביעי. hu
yitchata bo bayom hashlishi uvayom hashvii. The sprinkling of the פרה אדומה
parah adumah is called יתחטא. yitchata.
So חטא חיטוי cheit chitoi means cleansing. So I so the real
the real question here is I do not meaning I think it's
very clear I do not think this is apologetics at all if
you look at you know the academics it's פשט pshat and the
פשטנים pshtanim it's פשט pshat in the פסוקים psukim that חיטוי chitoi
is about cleansing not about sin but about cleansing. Cleansing can be
sin cleansing can be טומאה. tumah. So the real question is why
does the יולדת yoledes become טמא? tamei? Okay but that's like I
think a separate discussion. That at least I I really do not
believe at all this is apologetics. I believe it's פשט. pshat. All
right and I believe that it's reinforced by many different things that
focus on חטאת chatas as cleansing. Anyway back to the point. So
that's in a way the issue here but you could say that
that's exactly the way the גמרא Gemara is framing the debate. If
you view it just as a cleansing act like טבילה tevilah who
cares what thing you designate for? You did the cleansing act at
the end it it cleanses the sin the טומאה tumah not the
sin the טומאה. tumah. If you view it as some type of
a sin thing so then maybe it has to דווקא davka relate
to the last in order to be effective. That is what you
could see as the debate here. So let's take a look at
how the גמרא Gemara responds. Of course the problem is that if
it's about sin you would need it for all of them. So
let's take a look at how the גמרא Gemara responds. אמר רב
פפא. Amar Rav Pappa. So Rav Pappa said אי סלקא דעתך... ei
salka da'atach... of רבי יוחנן בן נורי, Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri,
if he says that it's like a חטאת chatas and therefore it
has to be at the end, אמאי שבע ספק תביא אחת ותיפטר,
amai sheva safeik tavi achas vetipater,
why in the case of ספק safeik can you say it works
for you can designate it for any one of the previous ones?
That doesn't work, it would still have to be at the end
because maybe the ספק safeik are חייב. chayav. אי למאן דחייב ee
l'man d'chayiv and here's a comparison, somebody who's obligated חמש אשמות תלויים,
chamesh ashamot teluyim, let's say it was what would be the comparison
in the world of sin? Five אשם תלוי, asham talui, right? Each
one of them is for like a doubtful sin. So there too
you wouldn't say you're done with your obligation when you bring it
for any one of them. כי מייתי חד מיפטר, ki mayisi chad
mipater, you're not exempt when you bring one. And when ותניא זה
הכלל, v'tanya zeh haklal, here's the principle, כל שחלוקין בחטאת חלוקין באשם,
kol shechalukin b'chatas chalukin b'asham, that if you have a different חטאת
chatas you have a different אשם asham and it basically functions like
a חטאת. chatas. So if by a חטאת chatas it needs to
go for all of them, by an אשם asham you would need
all five אשמות ashamot to be cleansed. So why is he more
lenient in a case of ספק safeik that it could be for
a middle one if it really is similar to the sin model
and not the cleansing model? So אלא ella you can't say that.
And anyway what I would reinforce also is why does he allow
one to work? If it's really similar to the sin model, you
would need to bring all of them. אלא ella so that's פשט.
pshat. Here's the פשט. pshat. דכולי עלמא לטבילות מדמי להן. dechulei alma
l'tefilos midamei lehan.
Everybody agrees it's like going to the מקוה. mikvah. It's a cleansing
act. It is not about an atonement for the sin. ובחוששין לפשיעה
קמיפלגי. ub'choshshin l'pshia kamifligi.
So what's the issue about why when it's ודאי vadai do you
have to tell me I'm bringing for the last one? It's a
concern of the slippery slope or it'll lead to negligence. What will
lead to negligence? רבי יוחנן בן נורי סבר חיישינן, Rabbi Yochanan ben
Nuri savar chaishinan, רבי עקיבא סבר לא חיישינן. Rabbi Akiva savar lo
chaishinan. רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri is concerned, רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is not.
What is רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri concerned about?
רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri is concerned that if
I can have this case of five לידות leidos and I bring
it in June and I say, you know, this is going for
the January one, so I'm basically saying, okay, I had one birth
in January, I brought its חטאת chatas and I didn't have to
worry about the future births. Now the reason there you didn't is
because you brought it in June after the future births. But that
would lead you to the next time around, you know, saying a
woman has a birth in January, she brings her חטאת chatas and
then she says, yeah, I don't have to worry the next four
five five times I give birth because last time I didn't have
to worry also. So therefore no, you emphasize it goes at the
end that somehow more sends the message this is for everything that
preceded. Right? When it's for the last one you're saying only if
you're saying it's for the last one which means that only that
it works only for what preceded it doesn't work for what follows.
So that's why רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan wants to insist you do
it at the last so you don't make that mistake for the
next time around. Whereas רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says I'm not concerned
about that but basically in principle and that's why רבי יוחנן בן
נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri is lenient by a case of ספק
safeik because it's rarer and it's you know and we're not so
concerned about the next time around but in principle everybody agrees that
it's like the מקוה mikvah and you go once and that cleanses
whether you say it's for the beginning middle or end. Okay so
here the I think it's very important as a lead-in to the
next פרק perek because it really gets to the issue of a
חטאת chatas that is a not sin-based חטאת chatas although the גמרא
Gemara tried to frame that maybe in some ways it is and
the גמרא Gemara says no everybody really agrees it's just part of
the טהרה tahara process and therefore it doesn't matter whether you say
it's for the beginning middle or end when you do it it
cleanses what preceded and the rest just remains an obligation. Okay so
הדרן עלך שלשים ושש. hadran alach shloshim v'sheish. That is the end
of that and that's a perfect segue into the next פרק perek
which is about these cleansing and טהרה tahara חטאות chatasot and not
sin חטאות. chatasot. So let's take a look at the next פרק.
perek. ארבעה מחוסרי כפרה וארבעה מביאין על הזדון כשגגה. arba mechusrei kapara
v'arba mevi'in al hazadon kishgaga. There are four חטאות chatasot that are
for people that are lacking- now again the word here is atonement
but the point is and again you know this so this could
maybe be exactly the the tension that we spoke about before but
the phrase מחוסרי כפרה mechusrei kapara means that the lack of bringing
the חטאת chatas prevents them from becoming טהור. tahor. That is part
of a טהרה tahara process and without the חטאת chatas they can't
go into the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. They're mostly טהור tahor but
they can't go to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash or eat קדשים.
kodshim. So there are four that are about the purification process and
are not fundamentally about sin. וארבעה v'arba that's one special type of
a חטאת. chatas. וארבעה מביאין על הזדון כשגגה. v'arba mevi'in al hazadon
kishgaga. There are also four חטאות chatasot that you bring even for
a willful sin. Normally a חטאת chatas is only for an inadvertent
sin but there are four that are done even for a willful.
Let's take a look at these two special categories. ואלו הן מחוסרי
כפרה. v'eilu hein mechusrei kapara. These are the ones that are that
are those that that this is part of a טהרה tahara purification
process. הזב והזבה, hazav v'hazava, a male or female that has a
unusual flow. For male since there's not a a monthly cycle what
defines the flow as unusual you know a penile emission is what
it looks like that it's not semen it's something else. Okay so
and the there are certain ways you determine whether it's considered a
type of a זיבה ziva flow. Now some people think that this
is like some form of like a venereal disease or gonorrhea which
leads to certain types of flows but as we're going to see
in the גמרא Gemara the גמרא Gemara says that it only when
it only only when it comes out almost like through an almost
ejaculate in you know some some form of like ejaculation. And from
what at least what I understand, we have a doctor in the
room, the gonorrhea, the sort of flows that come out are specifically
like you know sort of not through an erection and ejaculation. Is
that true?
I actually I don't I don't know.
Yeah, I'm not certain.
Okay. Okay. Anyway, whatever it is, that it's defined as a non-semen
it's a non-בעל קרי baal keri because of the nature of because
of the you know the substance of of the emission. And a
זבה zavah is a flow of blood but it's not during the
normal menstrual period. So what defines it as a non-normal
flow is the fact that it's not during the normal during what
time of the month. And it's not during the normal menstrual period.
Both of these people, if it happens three times, become טמא tamei
and they cannot and it they can't eat קרבנות korbanot until there's
a seven-day cleansing process and then there's the bringing of a קרבן.
korban. And the bringing of the קרבן korban is what finishes the
process. Okay, and again here should be mentioned going back to Rivka's
point, that there's never any suggestion here that the חטאת chatas is
somehow sin-related. Okay, there's never the suggestion of sin, although there is
a idea of a חטאת. chatas. Illness. It's illness. Except the יולדת.
yoledet. Okay, so that goes more to what makes them similar in
the sense that they have the type of טומאה. tumah. That's a
discussion that I you know I'm prepared to have. Is it because
of an illness discussion aspect and then you say but what's the
illness of a יולדת, yoledet, right? Or is it because as others
what what? So concerning קרבנות. korbanot. Right, others have said that it's
not about illness, it's about the טומאה tumah relates to death. And
therefore death and so illness is one aspect that is associated with
death, right, you know, that's one thing. And the other thing though,
the childbirth is because
you know because it's like there was a I mean there's also
the נדה niddah in a way is a something that could have
been life and it wasn't, you know, that when a woman menstruates.
And that the childbirth, you could emphasize the idea that you know
that what do you call it that a woman actually is in
a you know it is in a risky health situation when you're
giving childbirth or that the very fact you know that that the
life and death aspects of childbirth even the life aspect sort of
touches on the world of death. Those are that's I think the
normal way those things are phrased. But you're right, I mean if
you only use the illness model, it makes the both the נדה
niddah and the יולדת yoledet very problematic. So but illness doesn't work
for the case of a dead carcass of an animal or a
dead human body. So the norm I think those that try to
understand a comprehensive theory about טומאה tumah emphasize more the idea of
death and things that surround it. And through that try to tie
it into the idea of נדה niddah and childbirth.
Yes. The Artscroll footnote cites a רמב"ם Rambam who says that זיבה
ziva is caused by disease
that occurs when the reproductive organs are weak but the rest of
the body is healthy. Okay.
So anyway, okay,
so
right, so definitely yes, but we'll see in a minute in the
גמרא Gemara anyway that my question was was it what we recognize
as a classic venereal disease and that's a little bit of a
problem based on the way the גמרא Gemara describes it in a
minute. Okay, so you have those two, the יולדת yoledet and המצורע,
hametzora, childbirth which we discussed in the last פרק, perek, and a
somebody who has צרעת. tzara'at. So those are all people that part
of the טהרה tahara process ends with the bringing of a קרבן
חטאת. korban chatas. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov
omer,
so those are the four מחוסרי כפרה. mechusrei kapparah. He says, גר
מחוסר כפרה שיזרוק עליו הדם. ger mechusar kapparah she'izrok alav hadam.
A גר ger has to bring a קרבן korban when we had
קרבנות, korbanot, and we will see in a minute that's part of
the process of becoming a גר ger is bringing a קרבן. korban.
So he says that part of that's also a מחוסר כפרה. mechusar
kapparah. A גר ger can't eat קדשים kodshim until he brings this
קרבן. korban. It's part of like a טהרה tahara process, okay, which
is an interesting idea which also sees the conversion process as a
sense of going from טומאה tumah to טהרה, tahara, you know, which
and therefore it's part of like a it's not just a transition
of state, but it's also a טהרה tahara process that now allows
to eat the קדשים. kodshim. There's something similar if you want to
make a comparison to the idea of you know putting כלים keilim
in a מקוה, mikvah, the type of a sense of although you
know that טומאה tumah to טהרה tahara type of an idea although
you know then it sort of frames the world as the Jew
is טהור tahor and non-Jew is טמא, tamei, which is you know
which is definitely an issue. Yes.
Now would a גירות geirus be complete without this?
So that's the גמרא Gemara is going to discuss. That so the
חכמים's Chachamim basic position is you need it for גירות, geirus, but
you don't necessarily need it for טהרה. tahara. It's not about becoming
טהור, tahor, it's about the status change. Okay, yes. Okay, so that's
the that and then he says I have a question.
The whole rest of the world is rabbinically טמא tamei I thought.
Yeah, but that's a
right, that's a rabbinic issue, but
that's right, that's about ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz,
that's true. נזיר ליין ותגלחת וטומאה. Nazir leyayno vetiglachat vetumato.
Also רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer adds a נזיר nazir at the end
of his נזירות nezirus brings a קרבן חטאת korban chatas to end
his נזירות. nezirus. And that נזירות nezirus allows him the end of
that allows him to drink wine, to shave, to become טמא. tamei.
So it seems like רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov
what he's really saying is I put in this category not just
things that make you טהור, tahor, I put in this category anything
that changes your status. So what can change your status? A קרבן
korban of a גר ger makes him Jewish, the קרבן korban of
a נזיר nazir makes him a non-נזיר, nazir, so he's broadening this
category not just about טהרה, tahara, but about status change. Okay, but
when it gets to גר, ger, it does sound like he's also
saying that even a גר ger cannot eat קרבנות korbanot and it
is also part of טהרה tahara as well. Let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. מאי שנא זב וזבה דמני להו בתרין משום
דחלוקה טומאתן. Mai shna zav v'zava d'mani lehu bitrein mishum d'chaluka tumasan.
Why does it count זב zav and זבה zava as two? Why
doesn't it just say זב, zav, זיבה ziva or something? Why does
it count them as two
categories? Because their טומאה tuma comes in very different ways. How does
your טומאה tuma come in different ways? דזב לא מטמא באונס. D'zav
lo metamei b'ones.
A זב zav is not טמא tamei if it's somehow an אונס,
oness, where you know sort of like an אונס, oness, forced is
the wrong word here, but somehow not willful or not something, something
that basically comes, you know, uncontrolled. And this is really where the
point being that if it comes as a sense that is, you
know, through a non-ejaculation and non-erection and it just comes because it's
sort of like, you know, oozing out of his body, then that
would not be considered זיבה. ziva. זיבה ziva comes through a sort
of, you know, erection and ejaculation. That's sort of the contrast here
between אונס oness and non-אונס. oness. וזבה לא מטמאה בראיות V'zava lo
metamei b'reiyas and
however a זבה, zava, if a woman bleeds, even if it's due
to some type of external factors or illness, it's still considered a
זבה. zava. So the question about זיבה ziva versus a male זב
zav and a female זבה, zava, אונס oness is one difference. And
another difference is וזבה לא מטמאה בראיות בימים. v'zava lo metamei b'reiyas
b'yamim. A זב zav is only טמא tamei if he sees three
consecutive times on three consecutive days. A זב zav is טמא tamei
if he sees three consecutive times, three times even if they're not
on three days, even three times on the same day. Okay, so
it's not about separate days, it's just about separate times. דתניא, D'tanya,
we learned in a ברייתא, Baraita, he says it's not an אונס
oness and it requires a, you know, distinct, good point, got it.
Okay, דתניא, d'tanya, מבשרו, mib'saro, if a זב zav sees from his
flesh, ולא מחמת אונסו, v'lo machmas onso, if it comes out some
like, you know, the strength of the flesh, the power and not
something that like is just like oozing out. Okay.
ומטמא בראיות כימים U'metamei b'reiyas k'yamim and he even separate sightings are
makes him טמא tamei even if they're not separate days. דתניא, D'tanya,
תלה הכתוב את הזכר בראיות ואת הנקבה בימים. tala hakatuv es hazachar
b'reiyas v'es hanekeiva b'yamim. By the male it speaks about seeing three
times, by the woman it speaks about ימים רבים, yamim rabim, multiple
days. So by the man it's just about seeing three times, by
the woman it's about three times in three distinct days. So those
are differences. וזבה מטמאה באונס V'zava metamei b'oness and as opposed to
that a זבה zava is טמא tamei even if it's through external
factors the bleeding. ולא מטמאה בראיות כימים. V'lo metamei b'reiyas k'yamim. And
it's not on just three sightings, it has to be three different
days. So therefore that's why זב zav and זבה zava are different
categories because their טומאה tuma is very different. Also the most obvious
difference is a זבה's zava טמא tamei because of bleeding and a
זב zav is טמא tamei because of the substance of what he
sees is different whereas by a זבה zava it's when she sees
not what she sees. Anyway, it's very different טומאות. tumos. גמרא Gemara
says מצורע ומצורעת נמי חלוקה טומאתן. metzora u'metzoras nami chaluka tumasan. So
there's a difference between a female and a male מצורע. metzora. What's
the difference? דמצורע טעון פריעה ופרימה. D'metzora ta'un peria u'fshima. A מצורע
metzora has to rend his clothes and let his hair grow wild.
דכתיב בגדיו יהיו פרומים וראשו יהיה פרוע, D'ksiv b'godav yihyu frumim v'rosho
yihye farua, his garments will be rent and his hair will grow
wild. ואסור בתשמיש המטה, V'assur b'tashmish hamita, he can't have sex, which
we learn it from that he has to וישב מחוץ לאהלו, v'yashav
michutz l'oholo, outside of his tent, which means that he can't be
with his wife in his house. He can't be intimate. So therefore
that's what applies to a male מצורע, metzora, but ומצורעת, u'metzoras, a
female מצורעת, metzoras, אינה טעונה פריעה ופרימה. eina teuna peria u'fshima. She
doesn't rend her clothes or let her hair grow wild. דתניא, D'tanya,
אין לי אלא איש. ein li ela ish. I only know that
a man can become a מצורע metzora because when the תורה Torah
describes the מצורע metzora of humans, it says איש כי יהיה בו
נגע. ish ki yihye bo nega. So אשה מנין? isha minayin? How
do I know even a woman could become a מצורע? metzora? שאומר
והצרוע והמצורע, She'omer v'hatzarua v'hametzora, that's seen as a more inclusive word,
it's anybody in צרעת. tzara'as. הרי כאן שנים, Harei kan shnayim, and
it even includes anybody, even a woman. So a woman could become
a מצורע. metzora. אם כן מה תלמוד לומר איש? Im kein ma
talmud lomar ish? Why does it say if a man becomes a
מצורע? metzora? נזקק הכתוב מענין שלמעלה לענין שלמעלה. Nizko hakatuv m'inyan shemalah
l'inyan shemalah. To say it's not about the immediate context where it
says a man is talking about becoming טמא, tamei, but it's about
the later discussion. The later discussion in the פסוקים pesukim is not
becoming טמא tamei but what you do when you're טמא. tamei. About
the hair growing wild and the rending of the clothes. So yes
it does say man, but that's not to say a woman can't
become a מצורע. metzora. It's to say that a woman does not
have to, she's טמאה, tamei, but she doesn't have to do all
of these practices. Is this where we're missing the tradition of מרים
Miriam as a, no, no. צרעת Tzara'as is מחוץ למחנה, michutz l'machaneh,
but she doesn't render clothes, let her hair grow wild or אסור
assur in sex. Those specific things. The normal aspects of טומאה tuma
of what a טמא tamei person can and can't do apply to
a woman, but the special behaviors of a מצורע, metzora, that not.
לומר איש פורע ופורע, Lomar ish poreia u'foreia, a man lets his
hair grow wild. wild and rends his clothes, ואין אשה פורעת ופורמת,
ve'ein isha parea u'faramas, and a woman does not do those, ומותרת
בתשמיש המטה, u'muteres betashmish hamita, and a woman is not prohibited in
sex, שנאמר shene'emar וישב מחוץ לאהלו שבעת ימים, v'yashav mikhutz l'ahalo shiva
yamim, he shall sit outside of his tent for seven days, ולא
מחוץ לאהלו לו ולא מחוץ לאהלו לה, v'lo mikhutz l'ahalo lo v'lo
mikhutz l'ahalo lah, not outside of her tent. So that's very interesting
to reflect on why we would think that none of those practices
would apply to a woman, only the טומאה tumah aspect but not
the more, you know, if you would, demonstrative things, but although the
תשמיש המטה tashmish hamita is not necessarily demonstrative, but not the things
that are not directly about טומאה, tumah, those somehow only apply to
the man. Anyway, so she's less limited... no, she's less restricted. She
is allowed to have sex, she doesn't have to rend her clothes,
she doesn't have to be unseemly to her husband, I imagine. So
that's interesting. Is... so the sex thing, maybe the sex thing does
have to do with the understanding that when it comes to sex,
you know, a woman is more, right, obligated to her husband and
therefore it would become somehow constricting the husband's rights and you don't
see it the same way in the reverse, although there does... the
husband has a מצות עונה, mitzvah onah, but yes, that is possible.
It doesn't explain the difference of פורע porea and פורם porem about
hair growing wild and rending the clothes. Maybe because she... she will
look not as nice. Right. Right, it could... but a woman could
also... right, although I'm not sure that maybe, but you could also
imagine a single woman is a מצורעת metzora'at and you still don't
have the פורע porea or פורם, porem, so I'm not sure it's
all about the husband, but yes, it could be about the sense
about how... if it's seemly or unseemly for a woman sort of,
you know, from a sexual context to be seen that way, that
could very well be part of it. Look, that's actually also, you
know, what you do essentially, you know, for like a סוטה, sotah,
right, you uncover the hair and whatever, so, you know, so right,
that could very well be a part of it. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this, הלכך נימנינהו בתרתי, hilkach nimninhu betartei, so now
the גמרא Gemara gets back to its main point, which is, oh,
if there's differences, why weren't they counted as two separate categories for
the... for the separate type of קרבנות? korbanot? So the גמרא's Gemara
answer is pretty obvious, זב וזבה דאיכא טומאתן חלוקה. zav v'zava d'ika
tumatan chaluka. By a זב zav and זבה, zava, the basic... the
way they become טמא tamei is fundamentally different. What is טומאת זב
tumah v'zav about? How does it happen? How does טומאת זבה tumah
v'zava happen? They're radically different, you know, one is about a certain
type of emission, the other is a type of blood, this way,
that way, they're completely different how you become טמא. tamei. מצורע ומצורעת
אין עיקר טומאתן חלוקה. metzora u'metzora'at ein ikar tumatan chaluka. But when
a female and male מצורע, metzora, they become טמא tamei the exact
same way, it's about certain spots on the body, האי כגריס והאי
כגריס, hai k'gris v'hai k'gris, they're both the same size spot, they're
the same appearance of the spot, the only difference is the behaviors
that come afterwards. But that's... but the basic טומאה tumah is the
same and therefore we're not going to count them as separate categories,
okay? So in terms of people that a קרבן korban is part
of the טהרה tahara process, we have a male and female זב,
zav, we have a מצורע metzora which you do have a male-female
variety but they're fundamentally one category, and we have the יולדת yoledes
which we talked about last time. There it's the... again, this חטאת
chatas which is called מחוסר כפורים mechusar kippurim part of a cleansing
process, but now we have רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben
Yaakov that talks about the גר. ger. Now you could have said
that according to him he's just broadening the definition, anything that's that
status change, because he also talks about נזיר, nazir, but what he
also said by גר ger was a גר ger sort of needs
this because... in order presumably to eat קדשים. kodashim. So presumably he
actually sees that it's relating to the sense of טומאה tumah which
this is cleansing. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this, רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר גר
מחוסר כפורים, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer ger mechusar kippurim, ותנא קמא
מאי טעמא לא תני גר? v'tana kama mai ta'ama lo tani ger?
Why did the תנא קמא tana kama not say גר? ger? כי
תני מידי דמשכחת ליה בקדשים, ki tani midi d'mashkachat lei b'kodashim, because
the תנא קמא tana kama was saying something that's about being able
to eat קרבנות, korbanot, טהרה tahara that allows you to now eat
קרבנות. korbanot. גר כי קמייתי קרבן לאכשורי נפשיה בקהל, ger ki kamayti
korban l'achshurei nafshei b'kahal, when a גר ger brings a קרבן, korban,
it's to make him fit to, you know, enter into the community,
meaning like to marry a Jew or, you know, a Jewish man
or a Jewish woman. So yes, it's part of the... it's part
of the conversion process, but it's not part of a טהרה tahara
process and therefore it's not relevant. ונזיר מאי טעמא לא תני? v'nazir
mai ta'ama lo tani? And how about נזיר? nazir? How about that?
When... when a נזיר nazir brings a קרבן, korban, right, it is
about allowing him to eat certain things, eat, you know, wine. So
the גמרא Gemara thinks it's about eating קדשים, kodashim, here it allows
him to eat wine. So the answer is obvious, לא סוף סוף
נזיר נמי כי מייתי קרבן לאישתרויי ביין דחולין הוא. lo sof sof
nazir nami ki mayti korban l'ishtruyei b'yayin d'chulin hu. A נזיר nazir
brings a קרבן korban to allow him to drink wine, but not
to drink... but wine that's not sanctified. So again, for... for the
תנא קמא tana kama the definition of מחוסר כפורים mechusar kippurim is
not a חטאת chatas that is about status change, it's a חטאת
chatas that's about cleansing and becoming טהור. tahor. Yes, there are other
חטאות chataos that affect status change, but they're not about טהרה. tahara.
And... and רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov has a
broader definition. So now the גמרא Gemara says, רבי אליעזר דקתני נזיר
למישרי נפשיה,
Rabbi
Eliezer d'katani nazir
l'mishrei nafshei, so רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer then is saying the נזיר
nazir that he brings a קרבן korban because it now ends נזירות
nezirus and lets him eat, you know, drink wine,
ניתני נמי נזיר טמא, nisni nami nazir tamei, why didn't you take
the example of a נזיר טמא nazir tamei who brings a חטאת
chatas in order to sort of get out, you know, to address
the fact that he's become טמא tamei and now to... to begin
becoming a נזיר טהור nazir tahor again? Right, if a נזיר nazir
became טמא... tamei... When a נזיר טמא *Nazir tamei* has to bring,
right, the Torah speaks about the קרבנות korbanos *korbanos* that a נזיר
*Nazir* brings if he became טמא *tamei*. The reason, the, those קרבנות
korbanos *korbanos* are not what makes him טהור tahor, *tahor*. His טומאה
*tumah*, the טומאה *tumah* of a נזיר טמא *Nazir tamei* is still
טומאת מת *tumas meis*. He came in contact with a dead body.
How do you get rid of טומאת מת *tumas meis*? You get
sprinkled with the ashes of פרה אדומה parah adumah, *Parah Adumah*. You're
done. There's no קרבן korban *korban* that makes you טהור tahor. *tahor*
for טומאת מת *tumas meis*. The קרבנות korbanos *korbanos* that a נזיר
טמא *Nazir tamei* brings is to basically, you know, rectify the sin
of having become טמא *tamei* and to begin now becoming a נזיר
טהור tahor, *Nazir tahor*. But it is not about a status change
of removing the טומאה *tumah*. The removing the טומאה *tumah* just happens
because he became טמא מת *tamei meis*. And so therefore it's not
about removing טומאה *tumah*. It's not about becoming, you know, you know,
it's not about like a new definition of a person like going
from being a נזיר *Nazir* to a non-נזיר *Nazir* or a Jew
to a non-Jew. It's just about getting back into the טהרה taharah,
*tahara* observance of נזיר *Nazir* and therefore that does not qualify for
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar? בן יעקב ben Yaakov *Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov*.
What again is important here is when, how do you define your
group narrowly or broadly where you're seeing a number of חטאות *chataos*
that are not about sin, that are about status change and related
ideas. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. Okay, תנו רבנן
*Tanu Rabbanan*. Now we're going to get to the גר'ס *ger's* discussion
which is a very interesting one. This is one of, a very
important גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*. There are not too many גמרות Gemaras *Gemaros*
about גרים geirim *geirim* and this is one of them. So let's
take a look. תנו רבנן גר ger מעוכב לאכול בקדשים עד שיביא
קינו *Tanu Rabbanan ger me'ukav l'echol b'kodashim ad sheyavi kino*. A גר
ger. *ger* cannot eat קדשים *kodashim* until he brings his, his קן
*kan* which means like a nest of birds. Okay, we're going to
see that a גר ger, *ger*, the קרבן korban, *korban* that a
גר ger, *ger* brings can be, is basically two birds, one for
a, one for a חטאת chatas, *chatas* and one for an עולה
olah, *olah*. So he can't eat קדשים *kodashim* until he brings them.
עד שיביא קינו *Ad sheyavi kino*. הביא פרידה אחת שחרית *Heivi pereidah
achas shacharis*.
But however, as long as he brings one, like we discussed just
a minute ago by a יולדת *yoledes*, if she brings one out
of the five
that she's obligated, one is enough to make her טהורה *tehorah*.
So here too by a גר ger *ger*, although he's supposed
to bring two, if he brings just one of them in the
morning, אוכל בקדשים לערב *ochel b'kodashim l'erev*. Then he can eat קדשים
*kodashim* at night. I'm sorry, I said that he brings a
חטאת chatas *chatas* and an עולה olah, *olah*. We're going to actually
see, excuse me, it's going to be two עולות olos.
*olos*. Excuse me. So, so a גר ger *ger*, two עולות olos.
*olos*. Anyway, as long as he brings one, that is enough to
make him טהור *tahor* even if he has not yet brought the
second one. Okay. כל הקינים שבתורה אחת חטאת chatas, ואחת עולה olah.
*Kol hakinim shebaTorah achas chatas v'achas olah*. Right, here it says. Normally
in the Torah whenever two birds are brought, as, you know, obligatory,
sometimes an obligation to bring two birds, one is a חטאת *chatas*,
one is an עולה olah *olah*. כאן שתי עולות *Kan shtei olos*.
Here they are both עולות *olos*. Okay, that is the קרבן korban
*korban* of a גר ger *ger*. הביא חובתו מן הבהמה *Heivi chovaso
min habeheimah*. Now let's say instead of bringing two bird עולות *olos*,
he brings a cow as an עולה olah, *olah*. So יצא *yatza*.
That's fine. It doesn't have to be two, as we're going to
see in a minute, fundamentally it has to be an עולה olah.
*olah*. As we see, if you even as soon as you bring
one bird of an עולה olah *olah*, he is טהור *tahor* and
it just, the second is just an additional obligation. So therefore the
fundamental idea is bringing an עולה olah, *olah*.
To bring two עולות *olos* as the גמרא Gemara *Gemara's* going to
frame it is a leniency. Fundamentally he should be obligated to bring
like a large animal, a בהמה beheimah *beheimah*
as an עולה olah, *olah*, but if he brings two birds, he's
also okay and even one bird makes him טהור *tahor*. Okay, so
therefore if he wants
to bring a
בהמה beheimah *beheimah*, he's fine even if he just brought one. יצא
*Yatza*. עולה ושלמים olah v'shlamim. יצא *Olah u'shelamim yatza*. Now that's pretty
obvious. If he brings two בהמות *beheimos*, one's an עולה olah, *olah*
and one's a שלמים shlamim. *shelamim*, he's יצא *yatza*. Obviously if one's
an עולה olah, *olah* he's יצא *yatza*, an עולה olah *olah* and
a שלמים *shelamim* he's יצא *yatza*. But the point of this is
the next line. מנחה minchah? ושלמים לא יצא *Mincha u'shelamim lo yatza*.
Let's say he brings two things, neither of which is a bird
and neither of which is a, is an עולה olah, *olah*. Okay,
he brings a big cow as a שלמים *shelamim* and he brings
a מנחה minchah. *mincha*. So even though that cost him a thousand
times as much as two birds, it doesn't matter. You didn't bring
an עולה olah *olah*. The key is bringing an עולה olah, *olah*.
Okay, if it's birds, two עולות *olos* although one suffices to make
you טהור *tahor*, and if it's other things, an animal, even one,
but if you spend a lot of money but if you don't
bring an עולה olah *olah*, it doesn't work. Birds can't be שלמים
*shelamim*? Birds cannot be שלמים *shelamim*, only עולה olah. *olah* or חטאת
*chatas*. Okay. לא אמרו כאן *Lo amru kan*. They only meant that
they said two birds, אלא להקל *ela l'hakel*, to go easy on
him, to say that it doesn't have to be two large animals
or even one large animal. But of course if you brought a
cow or a sheep as an עולה olah *olah*, you are יצא
*yatza* as long as it's an עולה olah. *olah*. Yes. חס ושלום
*Chas v'shalom* to convert when there is a Temple and then you
have to pay. Right. Okay, well played. So now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says like this. Okay, of course, so let's take a look.
מאי שנא מנחה minchah, ושלמים דלא יצא *Mai shna mincha u'shelamim d'lo
yatza*? Why are you not יצא *yatza* with a מנחה minchah *mincha*
and a שלמים *shelamim*? Where do we know it has to be
an עולה olah, *olah*? דכתיב כאשר תעשו כן יעשה ka'asher ta'asu ken
ye'aseh. *Dichsiv ka'asher ta'asu kein ye'aseh*. So the Torah speaks about when
it speaks about becoming a גר ger. *ger*, או לעשות אשה ריח
ניחוח isheh rei'ach nichoach. *o la'asos isheh rei'ach nicho'ach*. The Torah says
like this. Speaks about, okay, like this. במדבר *Bamidbar* 15:14. Yeah, I'm
looking for, thank you. Okay, right. Just says, thank you. It says,
so this is talking about the whole thing where it talks about
bringing נסכים *nesachim*, the wine and the flour that comes with קרבנות
korbanos, *korbanot*. And it says, וכי יגור אתכם גר ger או אשר
בתוככם לדרתיכם ועשה אשה isheh ריח ניחח לה' *vechi yagur itchem ger
o asher betochechem ledoroteichem ve'asa ishe reiach nichoach l'Hashem*, when a גר
ger. *ger* is among you and brings a קרבן korban, *korban*, כאשר
תעשו כן ken, יעשה *ka'asher ta'asu ken ya'aseh*, like you do he
should do, the same way you bring שלמים *shelamim*, you bring wine
and flour with your קרבנות korbanos, *korbanot*, he should also. הקהל חקה
אחת לכם ולגר הגר חקת עולם לדרתיכם ככם כגר יהיה kachem kager
yihyeh, לפני ה' *hakahal chuka achat lachem velager hagar chukat olam ledoroteichem
kachem kager yihye lifnei Hashem*, like you like the גר ger *ger*
is all one law. So the פשט *pshat* of that פסוק pasuk,
*pasuk* is that a גר ger *ger* has to bring with his
קרבנות *korbanot* like a naturally born Jew has to bring flour and
wine. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is how reading it, oh, a גר
ger *ger* when somebody becomes a גר ger *ger*, he also has
to bring a קרבן korban. *korban*. Since it's in the context of
bringing קרבנות *korbanot*, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is reading it that part
of becoming a גר ger. *ger* is bringing a קרבן korban. *korban*.
That's how the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* is reading it. And now we're
going to say which, so כאשר תעשו כן יעשה *ka'asher ta'asu ken
ya'aseh*, like you did when you became Jewish. How, where did you
bring a קרבן korban, *korban* when you became Jewish? He has to
do like you did. What did you do? מה אתם עולה olah
ושלמים אף גר ger. עולה olah. ושלמים *ma atem ola ushelamim af
ger ola ushelamim*. When you became Jewish, you brought an עולה olah
*ola* and שלמים *shelamim*, he too. Where did we bring an עולה
olah, *ola* and שלמים *shelamim*? At הר סיני Har Sinai, *Har Sinai*.
Right, what does it say at הר סיני Har Sinai *Har Sinai*?
It says there at the end of משפטים mishpatim, *Mishpatim*, it says
ויזבחו זבחים שלמים לה' פרים *vayizbechu zvachim shelamim l'Hashem parim*, right, וישלח
את נערי בני ישראל *vayishlach et na'arei Bnei Yisrael*, משה Moshe *Moshe*
slaughtered these animals, they brought שלמים *shelamim* and עולות *olot*, ויזבחו *vayizbechu*...
what does it say? Just says the פסוק *pasuk*... ויזבחו פרים לה'
*vayizbechu parim l'Hashem*... now it's flown out of my head. Anyway, it'll
come back. Anyway, it says there that they brought cows and it
was זבחים *zvachim* which means שלמים *shelamim* and עולות *olot*. So therefore
we learn that that's what they were brought at the foot of
הר סיני Har Sinai *Har Sinai*. Since this פסוק *pasuk* talks about
a גר ger, *ger* bringing קרבנות *korbanot*, we're reading it to say
not what happens if he brings קרבן korban, *korban*, but when he
becomes a גר ger *ger*, he must bring a קרבן korban, *korban*,
and the קרבן korban. *korban* is like the קרבן korban? *korban* you
brought. And the קרבן korban *korban* you brought at the foot of
הר סיני Har Sinai, *Har Sinai*, and remember at that time, what
was the... it was explicit, what did they use the blood of
the קרבן korban *korban* for? To create the ברית bris, *brit* between
בני ישראל *Bnei Yisrael* and God. Right, משה *Moshe* sprinkles the blood
and he says, you know, and he says that זה דם הברית
dam habris, אשר כרת ה' עמכם על כל הדברים *zeh dam habrit
asher karat Hashem imachem al kol hadevarim*. So it was about the
relationship with God and becoming Jewish and obligations. And this is what
a גר ger. *ger* also brings, a קרבן korban, *korban* like you
brought. So in principle it should be an עולה olah. *ola* and
a שלמים *shelamim*. What? Two birds? Thank you. Right. ויעלו עלות ויזבחו
זבחים שלמים פרים לה' *vaya'alu olot vayizbechu zvachim shelamim parim l'Hashem*. Thank
you. Okay, so anyway, אף גר ger. עולה ושלמים *af ger ola
ushelamim*. Even a גר ger *ger* has to do in principle the
same. אם כן חובתו אחת מן הבהמה לא תסגי ליה *im ken
chovato achat min habehema lo tisgi lei*. Why, if he's bringing cows
or whatever sheep, why is it enough to bring an עולה *ola*?
Why don't we always insist on an עולה *ola* and a שלמים
*shelamim*? Just like you brought an עולה *ola* and שלמים *shelamim*, he
should have to bring an עולה *ola* and a שלמים *shelamim*. So
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, וגבי *vegabei*, it shouldn't be enough for him,
דכתיב כאשר תעשו כן יעשה *dechtiv ka'asher ta'asu ken ya'aseh*, you have
to do, he has to do like you had to do. אמר
רב פפא יש לומר לעוף איצטריכי לעולות בהמה לא כל שכן *amar
Rav Papa yesh lomar le'of itzterichi le'olot behema lo kol sheken*. No,
once we're going to see in a minute that he's even allowed
to bring birds, so if he can even bring birds, obviously we're
going easy on him, we don't demand exactly the same. And somehow
we're going to assume that if he can bring birds and there's
no such thing as a bird שלמים *shelamim*, and we're not going
to make up, you know, and we're not going to say a
חטאת *chatat* unless it starts explicitly about a חטאת *chatat*. So therefore
if we're going to say birds, we're going to say two עולות
*olot* birds and we're going that easy, presumably even when he brings
a בהמה *behema*, one is enough and it's enough to focus on
the עולה *ola* and not on the שלמים *shelamim*. Again, it's a
little unclear, you know, you might still say two and two and
you still need the same number, but that's גמרא Gemara *Gemara* saying
once we're going so easy to say birds as we'll see in
a minute, we're also not going to insist if it's a בהמה
*behema* then one should be enough even and the עולה *ola* suffices.
He's still required to bring two, it's just the first one... not
for בהמה *behema*. Which is for birds he's required to bring two,
one finishes the process, but for בהמה *behema* one is completely enough.
Okay, so we'll see in the end the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
also going to learn from some פסוקים *psukim*. Okay, one bull as
עולה *ola* fulfills both obligations? Yeah, he doesn't have both obligations. גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* sort of understands the obligation is either two birds or
one בהמה עולה *behema ola*. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says,
אי הכי *ei hachi*, if we're going that easy on him, מנחה
minchah נמי *mincha nami*, so let him bring a מנחה minchah *mincha*,
why does it have to be only an עולה *ola*? מידי כתיב
כן *midi ktiv ken*. It says, right, כאשר תעשו כן יעשה *ka'asher
ta'asu ken ya'aseh*. So in some ways it has to be the
same, it has to at least be an עולה *ola*. ועוף היכי
איצטריבי *ve'of heichi itzterivi*, now where do we know that an עוף
*of* satisfies? דתנו רבנן כאשר תעשו כן יעשה *detanu rabanan ka'asher ta'asu
ken ya'aseh*, like you've done he should do. מה אתם עולה ושלמים
אף הוא עולה ושלמים *ma atem ola ushelamim af hu ola ushelamim*.
In the same way you brought עולה *ola* and שלמים *shelamim*, him
too. שנאמר ככם kachem כגר *shenemar kachem kager*, like you like the
גר ger *ger*. מנין לרבות את העוף *minayin lerabot et ha'of*, how
do I know he can even bring a bird? תלמוד לומר talmud
lomar, אשה isheh. ריח ניחח לה' *talmud lomar ishe reiach nichoach l'Hashem*.
איזהו דבר שכולו לה' *eizehu davar shekulo l'Hashem*, what is something that
is all to God? Right, because that's in the context of where
it says in במדבר *Bamidbar*, he has to do like you had
to do, again the context is bringing נסכים *nesachim*, but it says
an אשה ריח ניחח *ishe reiach nichoach*, a burnt offering. to God.
So what is the one thing that is the prime idea of
an אשה, completely for the fire? הוי אומר hevei omer זה עולת
העוף zeh olas ha'of or זה עולה. zeh olah. Okay, so basically
what we're saying is, so, so the אשה is emphasized as עולה,
and because that's understood to be an extra פסוק, it's telling you
anything that constitutes an עולה, even a bird עולה. So from the
ככם we have this, we start with the model of עולה ושלמים.
But from the idea of אשה ריח ניחוח להשם isheh rei'ach nichoach
l'hashem we hone in on עולה and we say anything that's an
עולה, even a bird עולה. Okay, יכול שאני מרבה אף מנחה, yachol
she'ani marbeh af minchah, how about a מנחה? minchah. תלמוד לומר, talmud
lomar which isn't exactly an עולה and it's not completely burnt, it's
eaten by the כהנים, kohanim, part of it. Anyway, תלמוד לומר talmud
lomar כן, no, it's somewhat limited. So we are going to demand
an עולה, but we'll say any עולה, even a bird. One minute,
תניא אידך, tanya idach, we taught also similarly in a ברייתא, braisa,
יעשה אשה ריח ניחוח להשם, ya'aseh isheh rei'ach nichoach l'hashem, he shall
do a burnt offering to God. שומע אני כל שעולה לאישים, shomeia
ani kol she'olah l'ishim, anything that is burnt on the fire. כל
שעולה לאישים, kol she'olah l'ishim, אפילו מנחה, afilu minchah, maybe even a
מנחה. Again, it's funny, unless the הוה אמינא hava amina is that
some מנחה, like a מנחת כהן minchas kohen is completely burnt. Right,
so maybe that's the הוה אמינא, hava amina, maybe we should burn
it as a completely burn it as a מנחה and make it
like an עולה, make it like an אשה. So תלמוד לומר talmud
lomar כאשר תעשו כן יעשה. No, in one way it has to
be similar. מה אתם מיני דמים, mah atem minei damim, the same
way you brought קרבנות that had to do with blood, and again,
note emphasis, remember in the story at the foot of הר סיני,
Har Sinai, the blood was used as the דם הברית, dam habris,
as that sense of creating the covenant. אף הם מיני דמים, af
hem minei damim, so they also for a גר ger, as well,
it has to be some type of a קרבן korban. with blood.
So it's not be a מנחה even if it's a מנחה functioning
like an עולה, even if it's a fully burnt מנחה. אי מה
אתם עולה ושלמים אף הם עולה ושלמים, i mah atem olah v'shlamim
af hem olah v'shlamim, let's demand fully like it, it has to
be an עולה and a שלמים. תלמוד לומר ככם כגר יהיה, so
like you, like the גר. ger לכם הוקשנו, lachem hukashnu, yes, he's
like you, the person of the גר, ger ולא לקרבנותיכם, v'lo l'korbanoseichem,
but not that the קרבנות have to be identical. Which is a
little funny, where do you, it might emphasize you're like the גר,
ger the גר's ger like you, but it doesn't sort of say
the קרבנות are different. But anyway, before the גמרא Gemara learned it
from the ריבוי ribbuy of אשה ריח ניחוח. isheh rei'ach nichoach So
based on אשה ריח ניחוח we say that it hones in on
עולה, עולה suffices, and therefore it suffices if you're bringing a בהמה
to bring one עולה, and for a bird, however, two עולות. So
that's the next question, why by birds do you say two? Once
you've honed in on עולה and said that's the עיקר ikkar obligation,
where do you get the idea that if it's birds it has
to be two? So let's take a look. The גמרא, Gemara well
first the גמרא Gemara ends this ברייתא braisa and then we'll get
to the question of two. רבי אומר ככם כאבותיכם, Rebbi omer kachem
ka'avoseichem, you are like your fathers. מה אבותיכם לא נכנסו לברית אלא
במילה וטבילה והרצאת דם, mah avoseichem lo nichnesu labris ela b'milah u'tvilah
v'hartz'as dam, the same way you became גרים geirim, through, you know,
you became Jewish through circumcision, going to the מקוה, mikvah, and a
קרבן, korban? the ריצוי, ritzuy, the appeasement, the, or whatever, the, you
know, the, the blood making it, you, desirous to God. So somehow,
whatever, הרצאת דם hartz'as dam means, again, not at the same thing
as ריצוי. ritzuy. But ריצוי ritzuy is the classic term used by
the bringing of a קרבנות, what makes a קרבן korban. valid is
that God is רוצה, rotzeh, God desires in it. So הרצאת דם
hartz'as dam is a way of describing the bringing of a קרבן,
korban but again, the emphasis of blood, which was in the תורה
Torah at הר סיני Har Sinai? and also here that it has
to be a בהמה קרבן. korban, אף הם, af hem, similarly גרים,
gerim, לא יכנסו לברית אלא במילה וטבילה והרצאת דמים. lo yichnesu labris
ela b'milah u'tvilah v'hartz'as damim. So what did רבי Rebbi add? Until
now we've also been saying that a גר ger needs a קרבן.
korban, So it seems what he added is not the idea of
a קרבן, korban, but to also tell me that this model of
הר סיני Har Sinai, is also the model of where we learn
the other components of גירות. geirus. Not just the קרבן, korban, but
the idea of טבילה tvilah and מילה. milah. Now where that, we
know that in הר סיני, we'll talk about in a minute. But
that's what רבי Rebbi is adding, not just that a גר ger
needs a קרבן, korban, but we learn this as the paradigm of
גירות geirus and all of the components. And what do we do
today, the equivalent? The גמרא's Gemara going to ask that. So I'm
going to talk about that. The גמרא's Gemara going to ask that.
So להביא פרידה אחת אי אפשר, l'havi pereidah achas ee efshar, now
why don't we just say one bird? Right, we're turning to that
point. שלא מצינו בכל התורה כולה, shelo matzinu b'chol haTorah kullah, because
we never have in the תורה Torah just one bird קרבן. korban.
It's always two birds. Now the גמרא's going to question that. So
let's first finish the bird סוגיא sugya and then we'll focus on
the גר. ger ולא מצינו כאן אחד אלא להקל. v'lo matzinu kan
echad ela l'hakel. So the, so the birds are only to go
easy. Okay, so the גמרא, so our דוחק dochak on the idea,
so we focused on you need an עולה. So if it's an
עולה and it could be a sheep or cow, why when it's
a bird does it have to be two? And the answer is
because you never have just one bird. So the גמרא says, ולא,
v'lo, is that really true, you never have one bird? והתניא, v'hatanya,
we taught in a ברייתא, braisa, והקריבו, v'hikrivo, he should bring it,
the beginning of ויקרא, Vayikra, talking about the bird עולה. מה תלמוד
לומר? mah talmud lomar? לפי שנאמר בתורים והקריב, lefi shene'emar b'sorim v'hikriv,
since it says by the turtledoves you shall bring, שומע אני האומר
הרי עלי עולת העוף, shomeia ani ha'omer harei alai olas ha'of, if
somebody takes an obligation to bring a bird עולה, לא יפחות משני
פרידים, lo yifchos mishnei pereidim, maybe he has to bring two, because
תורים torim is in the plural and בני יונה benei yonah is
also in the plural. תלמוד לומר והקריבו and a חטאת, but here
we don't have a חטאת idea, so it's two עולות. So the
גמרא says, is that really true? והאיכא יולדת, ve-hika yoledes, how about
a woman in childbirth? דמייתי בן יונה אחד לחטאת, de-maysei ben yonah
echad le-chatas, she brings just one bird for her sin offering, right?
And the whole discussion before was about the birds, the price of
the birds and so on. So the גמרא says no, משום דאיכא
כבש בהדה, mishum de-ika keves bahadah, that even though she only brings
one bird, but she also brings a ram to go with it
as an עולה. So she brings an עולה and a חטאת, but
it's supposed to be two birds, it's a ram and a bird.
So that's even more of an expense. So we never find, though,
there's always a sense of a pairing. When a bird comes as
a חובה, chovah, it's always paired, sometimes two birds, sometimes a bird
and a sheep or something of that nature, but it's always paired.
So therefore here too, if the גר ger has to bring an
עולה, if it's a normal animal, one, but if it's a bird,
it will have to be two. Okay, that is the end of
the discussion of the עולה. Now we get to focus on this
as the model for the גר. I should just mention as before
we go further, that there is some question when רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer בן יעקב says that a גר needs this for טהרה, taharah,
does he agree to the חכמים Chachamim or do the חכמים Chachamim
agree to him? Does he say a גר becomes a גר without
the קרבן? korban The only purpose of the bird and the קרבן
korban is to make him טהור, or does he say no, the
קרבן korban? does both? It both makes him a גר and makes
him טהור. Okay, there's also the question about the חכמים. Chachamim. They
say we're not going to count it because it's about making him
a גר. But do they also say it does make him טהור,
but that's just not the major point? You know, how do they
see? So is, or do they, are they completely separate? One says
it's just about טהרה, taharah the other says it's just about becoming
a גר. That's for sure. What? The first one makes you a
גר, the second one makes you... Yeah, well, but we don't say
that. Nobody, everybody says one is enough. So anyway, I just want
to mention that there's that question in the ראשונים Rishonim how to
understand that. Let's now focus in on the גר issue. Okay, so
the גמרא says like this: אמר מר, amar mar, מה אבותיכם לא
נכנסו לברית, ma avoseichem lo nichnesu la-bris, the forefathers, you know, became
Jewish through מילה, milah, טבילה, tevilah, and a קרבן, korban. same with
a גר. בשלמא מילה דכתיב, bishlama milah de-chsiv, we know מילה milah
they became, they had, because it says כי מולים היו כל העם
היוצאים. ki mulim hayu kol ha-am ha-yotzim. When it says in יהושע
Yehoshua that before the קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, you know, that he
was נימול nimol everybody, it says that, yes, everybody was נימול nimol
when they left Egypt, but now nobody had gotten a מילה milah
for the forty years in the desert, so he had to do
a מילה, milah, a mass מילה milah before he brought the קרבן
פסח. korban Pesach. That's in the beginning of יהושע. Yehoshua. So therefore
you see, though... Yes, but it also says because, because when they
came out, they did have a מילה, milah, they just didn't have
it afterwards. So you see that when they came out, they all
had a מילה. milah. And presumably that's, and קרבן פסח korban Pesach
requires you to not be uncircumcised. So everybody who had the קרבן
פסח, korban Pesach, right, had done a ברית מילה. bris milah. אי
נמי מהכא, i nami me-hacha, ואעבור עליך ואראך מתבוססת בדמייך ואומר לך
בדמייך חיי ואומר לך בדמייך חיי, va-avor alayich va-erech misboseses be-damayich va-omar
lach be-damayich chayi va-omar lach be-damayich chayi, which we say is the
blood of מילה milah and the blood of a קרבן פסח. korban
Pesach. And therefore, if they're bringing קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, clearly they
all had a ברית מילה. bris milah. Now, I should mention by
the way, that the ראשונים Rishonim ask, you know, there's the famous
מדרש Midrash that לוי Levi did not need to do a ברית,
bris. did not need to, you know, did not need to do
a special for the קרבן פסח korban Pesach or whatever. They had
always kept the tradition of ברית מילה. bris milah. It was only
everybody else that needed a special מילה. milah. That's a very, you
know, a very widely accepted, you know, מדרש. Midrash. So the question
is, so לוי Levi did not do an act of מילה milah
in order to, in order to become, you know, this new entrant
into a ברית. bris, They did it because it was the tradition
handed down from אברהם. Avraham. So what a lot of ראשונים Rishonim
learn from that is, is that even if the ברית מילה bris
milah is not done for the sake of גירות, geirus, even if
it's done for the sake of Jewishness, that is enough for the
מילה milah of a גר. What does that mean? What's the relevance
of that? Let's say you have a baby born to an intermarried
couple, and the father's Jewish, the mother is not, and they want
to do a ברית מילה, bris milah, and the מוהל mohel comes
and does a ברית מילה, bris milah, and later they want to
do a conversion for the baby. If the מילה milah wasn't done
for the sake of גירות, geirus, but it was done for the
sake of a Jewish ברית מילה, bris milah, is that enough? Do
you need a separate sort of like, you know, drop of blood,
or does that count? And basically the consensus is that counts. That
you don't need an act of מילה milah as גירות geirus as
much as you need an act of מילה milah as like a
Jewish מילה. milah. Okay, but learned out from the fact that not
everybody in מצרים Mitzrayim or not all the Jews that came out,
the Israelites that came out, had it as a formal act of
מילה milah for the sake of גירות. geirus. Yes. That would seem
to have practical applications. One is, if someone did a Reform or
Conservative conversion and got a ברית מילה, bris milah, that that might
count for a halachic conversion. And second, a baby who was circumcised
in the hospital just because back in my generation everybody was circumcised,
that would not count. Right. That's basically correct. Yes. I mean, there's
other details in terms of responding to that, that also in the
hospitals before eight days, you know, there are questions about לכתחילה lechatchilah
wanting there to be a בית דין, beis din, but the basic
answer is correct. Yes. Okay, so that's important. But in this מעמד
ma'amad because you could say look, the בני לוי Bnei Levi were
doing it because they were descendants of אברהם Avraham and it was
part of the tradition. But in this מעמד, ma'amad, their becoming Jewish,
not just בני אברהם יצחק ויעקב Bnei Avraham Yitzchak v'Yaakov was through
this new thing of מילה, milah, טבילה, tevilah, and the קרבן. korban?
So they did not yet have a Jewish status and nevertheless the
מילה milah still counted. Now of course you could still say it's
different, even if they didn't have a Jewish status, they still had
a מצות מילה mitzvah's milah as opposed to somebody who doesn't have
a מצות מילה. mitzvah's milah. So I understand it's different, but I'm
still telling you that that is a very important הלכה halachic discussion.
It is a גמרא. Okay, anyway, that's מילה. milah. Now there are
three דמים. damim. How about a קרבן? korban דכתיב וישלח את נערי
בני ישראל, dechtiv vayishlach es na'arei Bnei Yisrael, everything we've been talking
about until now at the foot of הר סיני, they did the
קרבן. korban אלא טבילה מנלן? Ela tevilah minalan? How do you know
they went to the מקוה? mikvah? דכתיב ויקח משה חצי הדם ויזרוק
על העם, Dechtiv vayikach Moshe chatzi hadam vayizrok al ha'am, because he
sprinkled the blood on the people, ואין הזאה בלא טבילה. v'ein haza'ah
belo tevilah. So since when it comes to sprinkling it's a טהרה
taharah, process, like the ashes of a פרה אדומה, it requires טבילה,
tevilah, so we're assuming here the sprinkling of the blood required טבילה.
tevilah. Now of course there's a difference, because do you view, to
some degree maybe this is the debate of רבי אליעזר וחכמים, Rabbi
Eliezer v'Chachamim, do you view the blood and the קרבן korban we're
talking about as טהרה, taharah or do you view this as about
entering into a ברית, Bris? דם הברית, right? And a ritual of
entering, and then it's not so clear why you have טבילה. tevilah.
But that's the argument here. אלא מעתה, Ela me'ata, what? Sprinkling is
sort of a just a קרבן, korban right. The immersion would be
done beforehand, we do... No, the גמרא says you wouldn't have the
sprinkling unless it had been preceded by immersion. Okay, but that's if
you view the sprinkling as a טהרה process. So now the גמרא
says the question רבקה Rivka was asking, and we're just going to
go to the משנה. Mishnah. אלא מעתה האידנא דליכא קרבן לא נקבל
גרים? Ela me'ata ha'idna delika korban lo nekabel gerim? Nowadays we don't
have a קרבן, korban, let's not have גרים, since you're saying it's
a requisite, not just an obligation, but it's required? So אמר רב
אחא בר יעקב, Amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov, ככם כגר יהיה לכם
גר אשר בתוככם. Kachem kager yihiyeh lachem ger asher betochechem. It says
a גר that is in your midst, from which we learn that
there could always be a גר in our midst and we can
always accept a גר, so from which we infer that even when
you can't bring a קרבן, korban. it stops being a requirement. It's
only a requirement if it can be done. So let's just finish
this up. תנו רבנן גר בזמן הזה צריך שיפריש רובע לקינו. Tanu
rabanan ger bazman hazeh tzarich sheyafrish rova lekeino. Nowadays if somebody becomes
a convert, they have to set aside a רובע, rova, remember the
משנה Mishnah before spoke about ריבעתים, riv'atayim, like the quarter of a
silver דינר dinar was the cheap price of a bird sacrifice. So
a גר nowadays who becomes a גר has to set that money
aside so that when the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash is rebuilt, he'll
be able to bring his קרבן, which is interesting. So even though
it's not requisite for him to be a גר now, it still
remains an obligation and he'll have to satisfy it when the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash is rebuilt. אמר רבי שמעון, Amar Rabbi Shimon, or
רבי אלעזר? Yes, well, that's right, because it's not so much, well,
maybe. אמר רבי שמעון, Amar Rabbi Shimon, כבר נמנה עליו רבן יוחנן
בן זכאי וביטלו. Kvar nimna alav Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai uvitlo. רבן
יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai nullified that practice. רבן יוחנן
בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai nullified a few practices that were
similar, anyway that's the discussion, מפני התקלה, mipnei hatakalah, because of the
error or the stumbling. What's the stumbling? You'll sanctify the money and
then you'll come to do מעילה me'ilah with that money. So אמר
רב אידי בר גרשום אמר רב אדא בר אהבה הלכה כרבי שמעון.
Amar Rav Idi bar Gershom amar Rav Adda bar Ahava halacha k'Rabbi
Shimon. We rule that way, that we don't do that. ואיכא דמתני
לה אהא דתניא. V'ika demasni lah aha d'tanya. Some say it on
the following. תנו רבנן גר תושב מותר לעשות מלאכה בשבת לעצמו כישראל
בחולו של מועד. Tanu rabanan ger toshav mutar la'asos melachah b'Shabbos l'atzmo
k'Yisrael b'cholo shel moed. Right, it says that when you have somebody
in your midst, you have on שבת Shabbos you have to let
the גר rest. That's not talking about a convert, that's talking about
a גר תושב, ger toshav, somebody dwelling in the land in ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So what does it mean you have to let
them rest? Can you prevent them from doing any מלאכה? melachah? So
says no, actually he can do מלאכה melachah for himself, he can't
work for you, but he can do מלאכה melachah for himself, like
on חול המועד Chol HaMoed where we allow certain types of מלאכה
melachah if it's a דבר האבד, davar ha'aved, if it's a loss
and so on. So that he is allowed to do even on
שבת. Shabbos. רבי עקיבא אומר כישראל ביום טוב. Rabbi Akiva omer k'Yisrael
b'Yom Tov. It's more restrictive. It's only he can do מלאכה melachah
like a Jew would do on יום טוב, Yom Tov, meaning like
מלאכת אוכל נפש. meleches ochel nefesh. So when it says the גר
amongst you, again, not the convert, but the resident alien, you cannot
work on שבת, Shabbos, it means he can't work for you. For
him he can work in certain limited capacities. רבי יוסי אומר גר
תושב עושה בשבת לעצמו כישראל בחול. Rabbi Yosi omer ger toshav oseh
b'Shabbos l'atzmo k'Yisrael b'chol. If he's not working for you, if he's
working for himself, then he can do whatever he wants. The thing
that you have to let the גר rest is you can't make
him work for you. He can do whatever he wants for himself.
רבי שמעון אומר אחד גר תושב ואחד עובד כוכבים עבד ואמה תושבים
עושים מלאכה בשבת לעצמן כישראל בחול. Rabbi Shimon omer echad ger toshav
v'echad oved kochavim eved v'amah toshavim osin melachah b'Shabbos l'atzman k'Yisrael b'chol.
Whether it's a resident alien, whether it's your female or male slaves,
they do מלאכה melachah on שבת Shabbos for themselves, they can do
whatever they want for themselves. They can't work for you but they
can do whatever they want for themselves. So the statement that we
rule like רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, some say it was going on
the idea that a גר nowadays does not set aside the money,
some say it was going on this idea about a totally different
הלכה halachah about what somebody does on שבת, Shabbos, a resident alien.
Now I just want to say two final things about this. Number
one is why did we, why was there an assumption here that
of all the people that are obligated in a קרבן, a גר
sets aside the money as opposed to anybody else who... obligated in
a קרבן. And part of that is because that when there was
a בית המקדש, Bais HaMikdash, the קרבן was part of the conversion
process, which leaves hanging the question of is the גמרא suggesting that
if somebody converts and the בית המקדש Bais HaMikdash is rebuilt, that
their conversion is now not complete and they have to now do
this? Right? Because the גמרא assumed that there was a greater issue
of him leaving the money aside than of anybody else who also
has obligations. It sounds like it's not just an obligation, but that
it would become renewed part of the process. That's a very bizarre
idea. He's been a Jew until now and now it's a new
part, and now it's a new requirement? Okay, that's one issue. But
the point that I want to emphasize at the end is going
back to רבקה's Rivka question, which is, okay, are we just saying
we drop it? What replaces the idea of קרבן and what was
the function of קרבן? And what I think is very critical here
conceptually is, the גמרא here mentions מילה milah and טבילה. tvilah. What
does it not mention that we normally assume is part of the
process? What? ברית? bris Well, yes, קבלת מצוות. Kabbalas Mitzvos. Where's קבלת
מצוות Kabbalas Mitzvos here? And actually, if you look in classic sources
of גירות, geirus, a number of them don't mention קבלת מצוות Kabbalas
Mitzvos at all. One source does, but some sources only mention מילה
milah and טבילה. tvilah. And it's my theory that that is the
substitute for the קרבן. What is the idea of קרבן? What was
the קרבן about at the foot of הר סיני? It's after all
the משפטים, mishpatim, משה reads ספר הברית, Sefer HaBris, the עשרת הדיברות
Aseres HaDibros and the משפטים, and he says this, and then he
says this is the blood of ברית that God made with you
of all of these things. So it's creating the, it symbolizes you
are obligated in these מצוות, mitzvos, this is your relationship to God.
So that's what the קרבן is about. So if there's קרבנות, you
could say the bringing of a קרבן in the context of a
Jewish בית המקדש Bais HaMikdash and bringing a קרבן of God is
a similar type of statement, not as powerful as the foot of
הר סיני, but a statement about your relationship to God, your obligation
to God, and so on. When we don't have the קרבן, then
we, then an explicit act of קבלת מצוות Kabbalas Mitzvos becomes the
requisite sort of, you know, criteria that takes its place. That's my
understanding about how come these גמרות Gemaras don't mention and the גמרות
that do talk about קבלת מצוות Kabbalas Mitzvos don't talk about קרבן.
And that's how I sort of see what, you know, what now
takes the place. We will pick up with